<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="about">
  <title>About Nagios</title>

  <section>
    <title><anchor id="whatis" />What Is This?</title>

    <para>Nagios is a system and network monitoring application. It watches
    hosts and services that you specify, alerting you when things go bad and
    when they get better.</para>

    <para>Nagios was originally designed to run under <ulink
    url="http://www.linux.com/">Linux</ulink>, although it should work under
    most other unices as well.</para>

    <para>Some of the many features of Nagios include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Monitoring of network services (&protocol-smtp;, &protocol-pop3;, &protocol-http;, &protocol-ntp;, PING,
        etc.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Monitoring of host resources (processor load, disk usage,
        etc.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Simple plugin design that allows users to easily develop their
        own service checks</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Parallelized service checks</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ability to define network host hierarchy using "parent" hosts,
        allowing detection of and distinction between hosts that are down and
        those that are unreachable</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Contact notifications when service or host problems occur and
        get resolved (via email, pager, or user-defined method)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ability to define event handlers to be run during service or
        host events for proactive problem resolution</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Automatic log file rotation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Support for implementing redundant monitoring hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Optional web interface for viewing current network status,
        notification and problem history, log file, etc.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><anchor id="about-requirements" />System Requirements</title>

    <para>The only requirement of running Nagios is a machine running Linux
    (or UNIX variant) and a C compiler. You will probably also want to have
    TCP/IP configured, as most service checks will be performed over the
    network.</para>

    <para>You are not required to use the CGIs included with Nagios. However,
    if you do decide to use them, you will need to have the following software
    installed...</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A web server (preferrably <ulink
        url="http://www.apache.org/">Apache</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Boutell's <ulink url="&url-gd;">gd
        library</ulink> version 1.6.3 or higher (required by the <link
        linkend="thebasics-cgis-statusmap_cgi">statusmap</link> and <link linkend="thebasics-cgis-trends_cgi">trends</link>
        CGIs)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><anchor id="about-licensing" />Licensing</title>

    <para>Nagios is licensed under the terms of the <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GNU General Public
    License</ulink> Version 2 as published by the <ulink
    url="http://www.fsf.org/">Free Software Foundation</ulink>. This gives you
    legal permission to copy, distribute and/or modify Nagios under certain
    conditions. Read the 'LICENSE' file in the Nagios distribution or read the
    <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">online version of the
    license</ulink> for more details.</para>

    <para>Nagios is provided AS IS with NO WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, INCLUDING THE
    WARRANTY OF DESIGN, MERCHANTABILITY, AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
    PURPOSE.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><anchor id="about-acknowledgements" />Acknowledgements</title>

    <para>Several people have contributed to Nagios by either reporting bugs,
    suggesting improvements, writing plugins, etc. A list of some of the many
    contributors to the development of Nagios can be found at <ulink
    url="&url-nagios;">&url-nagios;</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><anchor id="about-downloading" />Downloading The Latest Version</title>

    <para>You can check for new versions of Nagios at <ulink
    url="&url-nagios;">&url-nagios;</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><anchor id="about-support" />Support</title>

    <para><ulink url="&url-nagios;support/">Support
    options</ulink></para>
  </section>
</chapter>

