<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="advancedtopics-cgiincludes" xreflabel="Custom CGI Headers and Footers">
	<title>Custom CGI Headers and Footers</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>If you're doing custom installs of Nagios for clients, you may want to have a custom 
		header and/or footer displayed in the output of the <link linkend="thebasics-cgis">CGIs</link>. 
		This is particularly useful for displaying support contact information, etc. to the end user.</para>
		<para>It is important to note that, unless they are executable, custom header and footer files 
		are not pre-processed in any way before they are displayed. The contents of the header and footer 
		include files are simply read and displayed in the CGI output. That means they can only contain 
		information a web browser can understand (HTML, JavaScript, etc.).</para>
		<para>If the custom header and footer files are executable, then the files are executed and their
		output returned to the user, so they should output valid HTML. Using this you can run your own custom 
		designed CGI to insert data into the nagios display. This has been used to insert graphs from rrdtool 
		using ddraw and command menus into the nagios display pane. The execuable customer header and footer
		files are run with the same CGI environment as the main nagios CGI, so your files can parse the query
		information, authenticated user information, etc. to produce appropriate output.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>How Does It Work?</title>
		<para>You can include custom headers and footers in the output of the CGIs by dropping some 
		appropriately named HTML files in the <filename class="directory">ssi/</filename> subdirectory of the Nagios 
		HTML directory (i.e. <filename class="directory">/usr/local/nagios/share/ssi</filename>).</para>
		<para>Custom headers are included immediately after the &lt;BODY&gt;&gt; tag in the CGI output, while 
		custom footers are included immediately before the closing &lt;/BODY&gt; tag.</para>
		<para>There are two types of customer headers and footers:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Global headers/footers. These files should be named <filename>common-header.ssi</filename>
				and <filename>common-footer.ssi</filename>, respectively. If these files exist, they will be
				included in the output of all CGIs.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>CGI-specific headers/footers. These files should be named in the format 
				<filename>CGINAME-header.ssi</filename> and <filename>CGINAME-footer.ssi</filename>, where 
				CGINAME is the physical name of the CGI without the .cgi extension. For example, the 
				header and footer files for the <link linkend="thebasics-cgis-summary_cgi">alert summary CGI</link> (<filename>summary.cgi</filename>)
				would be named <filename>summary-header.ssi</filename> and <filename>summary-footer.ssi</filename>, respectively. 
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>You are not required to use any custom headers or footers. You can use only a global header if you wish. 
		You can use only CGI-specific headers and a global footer if you wish. Whatever you want. Really.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

