<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="advancedtopics-clusters" xreflabel="Monitoring Service and Host Clusters">
	<title>Monitoring Service and Host Clusters</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Several people have asked how to go about monitoring clusters of hosts or services, so 
		I decided to write up a little documentation on how to do this. Its fairly straightforward, so 
		hopefully you find things easy to understand...</para>
		<para>First off, we need to define what we mean by a "cluster". The simplest way to understand 
		this is with an example. Let's say that your organization has five hosts which provide redundant 
		&protocol-dns; services to your organization. If one of them fails, its not a major 
		catastrophe because the remaining servers will continue to provide name resolution services. 
		If you're concerned with monitoring the availability of &protocol-dns; service to your 
		organization, you will want to monitor five &protocol-dns; servers. This is what I consider 
		to be a service cluster. The service cluster consists of five separate &protocol-dns; services 
		that you are monitoring. Although you do want to monitor each individual service, your main concern is 
		with the overall status of the &protocol-dns; service cluster, rather than the availability of 
		any one particular service.</para>
		<para>If your organization has a group of hosts that provide a high-availability (clustering) solution, I 
		would consider those to be a host cluster. If one particular host fails, another will step in to take 
		over all the duties of the failed server. 
		As a side note, check out the <ulink url="http://www.linux-ha.org/">High-Availability Linux Project</ulink> for 
		information on providing host and service redundancy with Linux.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Plan of Attack</title>
		<para>There are several ways you could potentially monitor service or host clusters. I'll describe 
		the method that I believe to be the easiest. Monitoring service or host clusters involves two things:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Monitoring individual cluster elements</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Monitoring the cluster as a collective entity</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Monitoring individual host or service cluster elements is easier than you think. 
		In fact, you're	probably already doing it. For service clusters, just make sure that 
		you are monitoring each service element of the cluster. If you've got a cluster of
		five &protocol-dns; servers, make sure you have five separate service 
		definitions (probably using the &plugin-dns; plugin). 
		
		For host clusters, make sure you have configured appropriate host definitions for 
		each member of the cluster (you'll also have to define at least one service to 
		be monitored for each of the hosts).</para><important><para>You're going to want to
		disable notifications for the individual cluster elements (host or service definitions).
		
		Even though no notifications will be sent about the individual elements, you'll
		still get a visual display of the individual host or service status in the 
		<link linkend="thebasics-cgis-status_cgi">status CGI</link>. This will be useful for
		pinpointing the source of problems within the cluster in the future.</para></important>
		
		<para>Monitoring the overall cluster can be done by using the previously cached results 
		of cluster elements. Although you could re-check all elements of the cluster to determine 
		the cluster's status, why waste bandwidth and resources when you already have the 
		results cached? Where are the results cached ? Cached results for cluster elements can 
		be found in the <link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-status_file">status file</link> 
		(assuming you are monitoring each element). The &plugin-cluster; plugin 
		is designed specifically for checking cached host and service states in the status file.</para>
		<important><para>Although you didn't enable notifications for individual elements of the
		cluster, you will want them enabled for the overall cluster status check.</para></important>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Using the check_cluster Plugin</title><para>The &plugin-cluster; plugin is designed 
		to report the overall status of a host or service cluster by checking the status information of each 
		individual host or service cluster elements.</para>
		<para>More to come... The &plugin-cluster; plugin can be found in the <filename class="directory">contrib</filename> directory of the Nagios Plugins 
		release at <ulink url="&url-sourceforge-projects;nagiosplug/">&url-sourceforge-projects;nagiosplug/</ulink>.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Monitoring Service Clusters</title>
		<para>Let's say you have three &protocol-dns; servers that provide redundant services on your 
		network. First off, you need to be monitoring each of these &protocol-dns; servers seperately 
		before you can monitor them as a cluster. I'll assume that you already have three seperate services (all 
		called "&protocol-dns; Service") associated with your &protocol-dns; hosts (called "host1", "host2" 
		and "host3").</para>
		<para>In order to monitor the services as a cluster, you'll need to create a new "cluster" service. However, before
		you do that, make sure you have a service cluster check command configured. Let's assume that you have a command 
		called check_service_cluster defined as follows:</para>
		<programlisting>define command{
        command_name    check_service_cluster
        command_line    /usr/local/nagios/libexec/check_cluster --service -l $ARG1$ -w $ARG2$ -c $ARG3$ -d $ARG4$
        }</programlisting>
		<para>Now you'll need to create the "cluster" service and use the <code>check_service_cluster</code> command you 
		just created as the cluster's check command. The example below gives an example of how to do this. The example 
		below will generate a CRITICAL alert if 2 or more services in the cluster are in a non-OK state, and a WARNING alert
		if only 1 of the services is in a non-OK state. If all the individual service members of the cluster are OK, the cluster 
		check will return an OK state as well.</para>
		<programlisting>define service{
	...
	check_command   check_service_cluster!"DNS Cluster"!1!2!$SERVICESTATEID:host1:DNS Service$,$SERVICESTATEID:host2:DNS Service$,$SERVICESTATEID:host3:DNS Service$
	...
	}</programlisting>
		<para>It is important to notice that we are passing a comma-delimited list of on-demand service state 
		<link linkend="thebasics-macros">macros</link> to the <code>$ARG4$</code> macro in the cluster check command. 
		That's important! Nagios will fill those on-demand macros in with the current service state IDs (numerical values, rather 
		than text strings) of the individual members of the cluster.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Monitoring Host Clusters</title>
		<para>Monitoring host clusters is very similiar to monitoring service clusters. Obviously, the main difference
		is that the cluster members are hosts and not services. In order to monitor the status of a host cluster, you
		must define a service that uses the &plugin-cluster; plugin. The service should not be associated with any of the hosts in the cluster, as this will cause problems with notifications for the cluster if that host goes down. A good idea might be to associate the service with the host that Nagios is running on. After all, if the host that Nagios is running on goes down, then Nagios isn't running anymore, so there isn't anything you can do as far as monitoring (unless you've setup <link linkend="advancedtopics-redundancy">redundant monitoring hosts</link>)...</para>
		<para>Anyway, let's assume that you have a <code>check_host_cluster</code> command defined as follows:</para>
		<programlisting>define command{
	command_name    check_host_cluster
	command_line    /usr/local/nagios/libexec/check_cluster --host -l $ARG1$ -w $ARG2$ -c $ARG3$ -d $ARG4$
	}</programlisting>
		<para>Let's say you have three hosts (named "host1", "host2" and "host3") in the host cluster. If you want 
		Nagios to generate a warning alert if one host in the cluster is not UP or a critical alert if two or more 
		hosts are not UP, the the service you define to monitor the host cluster might look something like this:</para>
		<programlisting>define service{
       ...
       check_command   check_host_cluster!"Super Host Cluster"!1!2!$HOSTSTATEID:host1$,$HOSTSTATEID:host2$,$HOSTSTATEID:host3$
       ...
        }</programlisting>
		<para>It is important to notice that we are passing a comma-delimited list of on-demand host state 
		<link linkend="thebasics-macros">macros</link> to the <code>$ARG4$</code> macro in the cluster check command. 
		That's important! Nagios will fill those on-demand macros in with the current host state IDs (numerical values, rather
		than text strings) of the individual members of the cluster.</para>
		<para>That's it! Nagios will periodically check the status of the host cluster and send notifications to you when
		its status is degraded (assuming you've enabled notification for the service). Note that for thehost definitions
		of each cluster member, you will most likely want to disable notifications when the host goes down . Remeber that 
		you don't care as much about the status of any individual host as you do the overall status of the cluster.
		Depending on your network layout and what you're trying to accomplish, you may wish to leave notifications for
		unreachable states enabled for the host definitions.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

