<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="advancedtopics-dependencies" xreflabel="Host and Service Dependencies">
	<title>Host and Service Dependencies</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Service and host dependencies are an advanced feature of Nagios that allow you to control the
		behavior of hosts and services based on the status of one or more other hosts or services. I'll explain
		how dependencies work, along with the differences between host and service dependencies.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Service Dependencies Overview</title>
		<para>There are a few things you should know about service dependencies:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>A service can be dependent on one or more other services</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A service can be dependent on services which are not associated with the same host</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Service dependencies are not inherited (unless specifically configured to)</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Service dependencies can be used to cause service check execution and service notifications
				to be suppressed under different circumstances (OK, WARNING, UNKNOWN, and/or CRITICAL states)</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Service dependencies might only be valid during specific 
				<link linkend="thebasics-timeperiods">timeperiods</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Defining Service Dependencies</title>
		<para>First, the basics. You create service dependencies by adding <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-servicedependency">service dependency definitions</link> 
		in your <link linkend="configuringnagios-configobject">object config file(s)</link>. In each definition you specify the 
		<emphasis>dependent</emphasis> service, the service you are <emphasis>depending on</emphasis>, and the criteria (if any) that cause the execution and
		notification dependencies to fail (these are described later).</para>
		<para>You can create several dependencies for a given service, but you must add a separate service dependency 
		definition for each dependency you create.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Example Service Dependencies</title>
		<para>The image below shows an example logical layout of service notification and execution dependencies. 
		Different services are dependent on other services for notifications and check execution.</para>
		<para>
		<informalfigure>
		<mediaobject>
	          <imageobject>
	            <imagedata fileref="images/service-dependencies.png" format="PNG"/>
	          </imageobject>
	        </mediaobject>
	    </informalfigure>
		</para>
		<para>In this example, the dependency definitions for <emphasis>Service F</emphasis> on <emphasis>Host C</emphasis> would be defined as follows:</para>
		<programlisting>
		define servicedependency{
		        host_name                       Host B
		        service_description             Service D
		        dependent_host_name             Host C
		        dependent_service_description   Service F
		        execution_failure_criteria      o
		        notification_failure_criteria   w,u
		        }

		define servicedependency{
		        host_name                       Host B
		        service_description             Service E
		        dependent_host_name             Host C
		        dependent_service_description   Service F
		        execution_failure_criteria      n
		        notification_failure_criteria   w,u,c
		        }

		define servicedependency{
		        host_name                       Host B
		        service_description             Service C
		        dependent_host_name             Host C
		        dependent_service_description   Service F
		        execution_failure_criteria      w
		        notification_failure_criteria   c
		        }
		</programlisting>
		<para>The other dependency definitions shown in the image above would be defined as follows:</para>
		<programlisting>
		define servicedependency{
		        host_name                       Host A
		        service_description             Service A
		        dependent_host_name             Host B
		        dependent_service_description   Service D
		        execution_failure_criteria      u
		        notification_failure_criteria   n
		        }

		define servicedependency{
		        host_name                       Host A
		        service_description             Service B
		        dependent_host_name             Host B
		        dependent_service_description   Service E
		        execution_failure_criteria      w,u
		        notification_failure_criteria   c
		        }

		define servicedependency{
		        host_name                       Host B
		        service_description             Service C
		        dependent_host_name             Host B
		        dependent_service_description   Service E
		        execution_failure_criteria      n
		        notification_failure_criteria   w,u,c
		        }
		</programlisting>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>How Service Dependencies Are Tested</title>
		<para>Before Nagios executes a service check or sends notifications out for a service, it will check to 
		see if the service has any dependencies. If it doesn't have any dependencies, the check is executed or 
		the notification is sent out as it normally would be. If the service <emphasis>does</emphasis> have one or more dependencies, Nagios
		will check each dependency entry as follows:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Nagios gets the current status<link linkend="advancedtopics-dependencies-hard_dependencies">*</link> of the service that is being <emphasis>depended upon</emphasis>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Nagios compares the current status of the service that is being <emphasis>depended upon</emphasis> against either 
				the execution or notification failure options in the dependency definition (whichever one is relevant
				at the time).</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>If the current status of the service that is being <emphasis>depended upon</emphasis> matches one of the failure 
				options, the dependency is said to have failed and Nagios will break out of the dependency check loop.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>If the current state of the service that is being <emphasis>depended upon</emphasis> does not match any of the 
				failure options for the dependency entry, the dependency is said to have passed and Nagios will
				go on and check the next dependency entry.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>This cycle continues until either all dependencies for the service have been checked or until one 
		dependency check fails.</para>
		<note><para>
			<anchor id="advancedtopics-dependencies-hard_dependencies"/>* One important thing to note is that by default, Nagios will use
			the most current <link linkend="thebasics-statetypes">hard state</link> of the service(s) that is/are
			being depended upon when it does the dependeny checks. If you want Nagios to use the most current state
			of the services (regardless of whether its a soft or hard state), enable the
			<link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-soft_state_dependencies">soft_state_dependencies</link> option.</para></note>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Execution Dependencies</title>
		<para>Execution dependencies are used to restrict when <link linkend="thebasics-activechecks">active checks</link> 
		of a service can be performed. <link linkend="thebasics-passivechecks">Passive checks</link> are not restricted
		by execution dependencies.</para>
		<para>If all of the execution dependency tests for the service passed, Nagios will execute the check of the service 
		as it normally would. If even just one of the execution dependencies for a service fails, Nagios will temporarily 
		prevent the execution of checks for that (dependent) service. At some point in the future the execution dependency 
		tests for the service may all pass. If this happens, Nagios will start checking the service again as it normally
		would. More information on the check scheduling logic can be found <link linkend="advancedtopics-checkscheduling">here</link>.</para>
		<para>In the example above, <emphasis role="bold">Service E</emphasis> would have failed execution dependencies if <emphasis role="bold">Service B</emphasis> is in a WARNING or 
		UNKNOWN state. If this was the case, the service check would not be performed and the check would be scheduled 
		for (potential) execution at a later time.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Notification Dependencies</title>
		<para>If all of the notification dependency tests for the service <emphasis>passed</emphasis>, Nagios will send notifications out for 
		the service as it normally would. If even just one of the notification dependencies for a service fails, Nagios 
		will temporarily repress notifications for that (dependent) service. At some point in the future the notification 
		dependency tests for the service may all pass. If this happens, Nagios will start sending out notifications again 
		as it normally would for the service. More information on the notification logic can be found 
		<link linkend="thebasics-notifications">here</link>.</para>
		<para>In the example above, <emphasis role="bold">Service F</emphasis> would have failed notification dependencies if <emphasis role="bold">Service C</emphasis> is in a CRITICAL
		state, <emphasis>and/or</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Service D</emphasis> is in a WARNING or UNKNOWN state, <emphasis>and/or</emphasis> if <emphasis role="bold">Service E</emphasis> is in a WARNING, UNKNOWN, or 
		CRITICAL state. If this were the case, notifications for the service would not be sent out.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Dependency Inheritance</title>
		<para>As mentioned before, service dependencies are not inherited by default. In the example above you can see
		that Service F is dependent on Service E. However, it does not automatically inherit Service E's dependencies on
		Service B and Service C. In order to make Service F dependent on Service C we had to add another service dependency
		definition. There is no dependency definition for Service B, so Service F is not dependent on Service B.</para>
		<para>If you do wish to make service dependencies inheritable, you must use the inherits_parent directive in 
		the <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-servicedependency">service dependency</link> definition. When this directive is enabled, it indicates that
		the dependency inherits dependencies of the service that is being depended upon (also referred to as the master 
		service). In other words, if the master service is dependent upon other services and any one of those dependencies
		fail, this dependency will also fail.</para>
		<para>In the example above, imagine that you want to add a new dependency for service F to make it dependent 
		on service A. You could create a new dependency definition that specified service F as the dependent service 
		and service A as being the master service (i.e. the service that is being dependend on). You could alternatively
		modify the dependency definition for services D and F to look like this:</para>
		<programlisting>
		define servicedependency{
		        host_name                       Host B
		        service_description             Service D
		        dependent_host_name             Host C
		        dependent_service_description   Service F
		        execution_failure_criteria      o
		        notification_failure_criteria   n
		        inherits_parent         1
		        }
		</programlisting>

		<para>Since the inherits_parent directive is enabled, the dependency between services A and D will be tested
		when the dependency between services F and D are being tested.</para>
		<para>Dependencies can have multiple levels of inheritence. If the dependency definition between A and D had
		its inherits_parent directive enable and service A was dependent on some other service (let's call it service G), the 
		service F would be dependent on services D, A, and G (each with potentially different criteria).</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Host Dependencies</title>
		<para>As you'd probably expect, host dependencies work in a similiar fashion to service dependencies. 
		The difference is that they're for hosts, not services.</para>
		<tip><para>Do not confuse host dependencies with parent/child host relationships. You should be using 
		parent/child host relationships (defined with the parents directive in <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-host">host</link> definitions) 
		for most cases, rather than host dependencies. A description of how parent/child host relationships work can be 
		found in the documentation on <link linkend="thebasics-networkreachability">network reachability</link>.</para></tip>
		<para>Here are the basics about host dependencies:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>A host can be dependent on one or more other host</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Host dependencies are not inherited (unless specifically configured to)</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Host dependencies can be used to cause host check execution and host notifications to
				be suppressed under different circumstances (UP, DOWN, and/or UNREACHABLE states)</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Host dependencies might only be valid during specific 
				<link linkend="thebasics-timeperiods">timeperiods</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Example Host Dependencies</title>
		<para>The image below shows an example of the logical layout of host notification dependencies. Different 
		hosts are dependent on other hosts for notifications.</para>
		<para>
		<informalfigure>
		<mediaobject>
	          <imageobject>
	            <imagedata fileref="images/host-dependencies.png" format="PNG"/>
	          </imageobject>
	        </mediaobject>
	    </informalfigure>
		</para>
		<para>In the example above, the dependency definitions for Host C would be defined as follows:</para>
		<programlisting>
		define hostdependency{
		        host_name                       Host A
		        dependent_host_name             Host C
		        notification_failure_criteria   d
		        }

		define hostdependency{
		        host_name                       Host B
		        dependent_host_name             Host C
		        notification_failure_criteria   d,u
		        }
		</programlisting>
		<para>As with service dependencies, host dependencies are not inherited. In the example image you can 
		see that Host C does not inherit the host dependencies of Host B. In order for Host C to be dependent on
		Host A, a new host dependency definition must be defined.</para>
		<para>Host notification dependencies work in a similiar manner to service notification dependencies. If 
		<emphasis>all</emphasis> of the notification dependency tests for the host <emphasis>pass</emphasis>, Nagios will send notifications out for the host
		as it normally would. If even just one of the notification dependencies for a host fails, Nagios will 
		temporarily repress notifications for that (dependent) host. At some point in the future the notification 
		dependency tests for the host may all pass. If this happens, Nagios will start sending out notifications
		again as it normally would for the host. More information on the notification logic can be found 
		<link linkend="thebasics-notifications">here</link>.</para>
	</section>

</chapter>

