<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="advancedtopics-escalations" xreflabel="Notification Escalations">
	<title>Notification Escalations</title>

	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			<inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/objects-contacts.png" format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
			</inlinemediaobject>Nagios
    supports optional escalation of contact notifications for hosts and
    services. Escalation of host and service notifications is accomplished by
    defining <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-hostescalation">host escalations</link> and 
    <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-serviceescalation">service escalations</link> in your <xref linkend="configuringnagios-configobject"/>.</para>

		<note>
			<para>The examples I provide below all make use of service escalation
      definitions, but host escalations work the same way. Except, of course,
      that they're for hosts instead of services. :-)</para>
		</note>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>When Are Notifications Escalated?</title>

		<para>Notifications are escalated if and only if one or more escalation
    definitions matches the current notification that is being sent out. If a
    host or service notification does not have any valid escalation
    definitions that applies to it, the contact group(s) specified in either
    the host group or service definition will be used for the notification.
    Look at the example below:</para>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      3
		        last_notification       5
		        notification_interval   90
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      6
		        last_notification       10
		        notification_interval   60
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers,everyone
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<para>Notice that there are "holes" in the notification escalation
    definitions. In particular, notifications 1 and 2 are not handled by the
    escalations, nor are any notifications beyond 10. For the first and second
    notification, as well as all notifications beyond the tenth one, the
    default contact groups specified in the service definition are used. For
    all the examples I'll be using, I'll be assuming that the default contact
    groups for the service definition is called nt-admins.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Contact Groups</title>

		<para>When defining notification escalations, it is important to keep in
    mind that any contact groups that were members of "lower" escalations
    (i.e. those with lower notification number ranges) should also be included
    in "higher" escalation definitions. This should be done to ensure that
    anyone who gets notified of a problem continues to get notified as the
    problem is escalated. Example:</para>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      3
		        last_notification       5
		        notification_interval   90
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      6
		        last_notification       0
		        notification_interval   60
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers,everyone
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<para>The first (or "lowest") escalation level includes both the nt-admins
    and managers contact groups. The last (or "highest") escalation level
    includes the nt-admins, managers, and everyone contact groups. Notice that
    the nt-admins contact group is included in both escalation definitions.
    This is done so that they continue to get paged if there are still
    problems after the first two service notifications are sent out. The
    managers contact group first appears in the "lower" escalation definition
    - they are first notified when the third problem notification gets sent
    out. We want the managers group to continue to be notified if the problem
    continues past five notifications, so they are also included in the
    "higher" escalation definition.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Overlapping Escalation Ranges</title>

		<para>Notification escalation definitions can have notification ranges
    that overlap. Take the following example:</para>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      3
		        last_notification       5
		        notification_interval   20
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      4
		        last_notification       0
		        notification_interval   30
		        contact_groups          on-call-support
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<para>In the example above:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The nt-admins and managers contact groups get notified on the third notification</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>All three contact groups get notified on the fourth and fifth notifications</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Only the on-call-support contact group gets notified on the sixth (or higher) notification</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Recovery Notifications</title>

		<para>Recovery notifications are slightly different than problem
    notifications when it comes to escalations. Take the following
    example:</para>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      3
		        last_notification       5
		        notification_interval   20
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      4
		        last_notification       0
		        notification_interval   30
		        contact_groups          on-call-support
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<para>If, after three problem notifications, a recovery notification is
    sent out for the service, who gets notified? The recovery is actually the
    fourth notification that gets sent out. However, the escalation code is
    smart enough to realize that only those people who were notified about the
    problem on the third notification should be notified about the recovery.
    In this case, the nt-admins and managers contact groups would be notified
    of the recovery.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Notification Intervals</title>

		<para>You can change the frequency at which escalated notifications are
    sent out for a particular host or service by using the
    notification_interval option of the hostgroup or service escalation
    definition. Example:</para>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      3
		        last_notification       5
		        notification_interval   45
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      6
		        last_notification       0
		        notification_interval   60
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers,everyone
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<para>In this example we see that the default notification interval for
    the services is 240 minutes (this is the value in the service definition).
    When the service notification is escalated on the 3rd, 4th, and 5th
    notifications, an interval of 45 minutes will be used between
    notifications. On the 6th and subsequent notifications, the notification
    interval will be 60 minutes, as specified in the second escalation
    definition.</para>

		<para>Since it is possible to have overlapping escalation definitions for
    a particular hostgroup or service, and the fact that a host can be a
    member of multiple hostgroups, Nagios has to make a decision on what to do
    as far as the notification interval is concerned when escalation
    definitions overlap. In any case where there are multiple valid escalation
    definitions for a particular notification, Nagios will choose the smallest
    notification interval. Take the following example:</para>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      3
		        last_notification       5
		        notification_interval   45
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      4
		        last_notification       0
		        notification_interval   60
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers,everyone
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<para>We see that the two escalation definitions overlap on the 4th and
    5th notifications. For these notifications, Nagios will use a notification
    interval of 45 minutes, since it is the smallest interval present in any
    valid escalation definitions for those notifications.</para>

		<para>One last note about notification intervals deals with intervals of
    0. An interval of 0 means that Nagios should only sent a notification out
    for the first valid notification during that escalation definition. All
    subsequent notifications for the hostgroup or service will be suppressed.
    Take this example:</para>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		       host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      3
		        last_notification       5
		        notification_interval   45
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
		        host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      3
		        last_notification       5
		        notification_interval   45
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<programlisting>
		define serviceescalation{
			host_name               webserver
		        service_description     HTTP
		        first_notification      7
		        last_notification       0
		        notification_interval   30
		        contact_groups          nt-admins,managers
	        }
		</programlisting>

		<para>In the example above, the maximum number of problem notifications
    that could be sent out about the service would be four. This is because
    the notification interval of 0 in the second escalation definition
    indicates that only one notification should be sent out (starting with and
    including the 4th notification) and all subsequent notifications should be
    repressed. Because of this, the third service escalation definition has no
    effect whatsoever, as there will never be more than four
    notifications.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Time Period Restrictions</title>

		<para>Under normal circumstances, escalations can be used at any time that
    a notification could normally be sent out for the host or service. This
    "notification time window" is determined by the <varname>notification_period</varname>
    directive in the <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-host">host</link> or 
    <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-service">service</link> definition.</para>

		<para>You can optionally restrict escalations so that they are only used
    during specific time periods by using the
    <varname>escalation_period</varname> directive in the host or service
    escalation definition. If you use the <varname>escalation_period</varname> directive to
    specify a <xref linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-timeperiod"/> during
    which the escalation can be used, the escalation will only be used during
    that time. If you do not specify any <varname>escalation_period</varname> directive, the
    escalation can be used at any time within the "notification time window"
    for the host or service.</para>

		<note>
			<para>Escalated notifications are still subject to the normal time
    restrictions imposed by the <varname>notification_period</varname>
    directive in a host or service definition, so the timeperiod you specify
    in an escalation definition should be a subset of that larger
    "notification time window".</para>
		</note>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>State Restrictions</title>

		<para>If you would like to restrict the escalation definition so that it
    is only used when the host or service is in a particular state, you can
    use the <varname>escalation_options</varname> directive in the host or service escalation
    definition. If you do not use the <varname>escalation_options</varname> directive, the
    escalation can be used when the host or service is in any state.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

