<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="advancedtopics-freshness" xreflabel="Service and Host Freshness Checks">
	<title>Service and Host Freshness Checks</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Nagios supports a feature that does <quote>freshness</quote> checking on the results of host 
		and service checks. The purpose of freshness checking is to ensure that host and service 
		checks are being provided passively by external applications on a regular basis.</para>
		<para>Freshness checking is useful when you want to ensure that
		<link linkend="thebasics-passivechecks">passive checks</link> are being received 
		as frequently as you want. This can be very useful in 
		<link linkend="advancedtopics-distributed">distributed</link> and 
		<link linkend="advancedtopics-redundancy">failover</link> monitoring environments.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>How Does Freshness Checking Work?</title>
		<para>
			        <inlinemediaobject>
		      <imageobject>
		        <imagedata fileref="images/freshness.png" format="PNG"/>
		      </imageobject>
		    </inlinemediaobject>
		Nagios periodically checks the freshness of the results for all hosts services that
		have freshness checking enabled.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>A freshness threshold is calculated for each host or service.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>For each host/service, the age of its last check result is compared 
				with the freshness threshold.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>If the age of the last check result is greater than the freshness 
				threshold, the check result is considered <quote>stale</quote>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>If the check results is found to be stale, Nagios will force an
				<link linkend="thebasics-activechecks">active check</link> of the host
				or service by executing the command specified by in the host or service definition.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<tip><para>An active check is executed even if active checks are disabled on a program-wide
		or host- or service-specific basis.</para></tip>
		<para>For example, if you have a freshness threshold of 60 for one of your services, Nagios
		will consider that service to be stale if its last check result is older than 60 seconds.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Enabling Freshness Checking</title>
		<para>Here's what you need to do to enable freshness checking...</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Enable freshness checking on a program-wide basis with the 
				<link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-check_service_freshness">check_service_freshness</link> 
				and <link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-check_host_freshness">check_host_freshness</link> directives.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use <link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-service_freshness_check_interval">service_freshness_check_interval</link> 
				and <link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-host_freshness_check_interval">host_freshness_check_interval</link> options to tell Nagios 
				how often in should check the freshness of service and host results.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Enable freshness checking on a host- and service-specific basis by setting
				the <varname>check_freshness</varname> option in your host and service definitions
				to a value of 1.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Configure freshness thresholds by setting the 
				<varname>freshness_threshold</varname> option in your host and service definitions.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Configure the <varname>check_command</varname> option in your host
				or service definitions to reflect a valid command that should be used to
				actively check the host or service when it is detected as stale.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The <varname>check_period</varname> option in your host and service
				definitions is used when Nagios determines when a host or service can be
				checked for freshness, so make sure it is set to a valid timeperiod.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<tip><para>If you do not specify a host- or service-specific <varname>freshness_threshold</varname> value 
		(or you set it to zero), Nagios will automatically calculate a threshold automatically, based 
		on a how often you monitor that particular host or service. I would recommended that you 
		explicitly specify a freshness threshold, rather than let Nagios pick one for you.</para></tip>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Example</title>
		<para>An example of a service that might require freshness checking might be one that 
		reports the status of your nightly backup jobs. Perhaps you have a external script that
		submit the results of the backup job to Nagios once the backup is completed. 
		In this case, all of the checks/results for the service are provided by an external 
		application using passive checks. In order to ensure that the status of the backup job
		gets reported every day, you may want to enable freshness checking for the service.
		If the external script doesn't submit the results of the backup job, you can have Nagios 
		fake a critical result by doing something like this...</para>
		<para>Here's what the definition for the service might look like (some required 
		options are omitted)...</para>
		<programlisting>define service{
		        host_name               backup-server
		        service_description     ArcServe Backup Job
		        active_checks_enabled   0               ; active checks are NOT enabled
		        passive_checks_enabled  1               ; passive checks are enabled (this is how results are reported)
		        check_freshness         1
		        freshness_threshold     93600           ; 26 hour threshold, since backups may not always finish at the same time
		        check_command           no-backup-report        ; this command is run only if the service results are <quote>stale</quote>
		        ...other options...
		        }</programlisting>
		<para>Notice that active checks are disabled for the service. This is because the
		results for the service are only made by an external application using passive checks. 
		Freshness checking is enabled and the freshness threshold has been set to 26 hours.
		This is a bit longer than 24 hours because backup jobs sometimes run late from day to 
		day (depending on how much data there is to backup, how much network traffic is 
		present, etc.). The <code>no-backup-report</code> command is executed only if the results of the
		service are determined to be stale. The definition of the <code>no-backup-report</code> command 
		might look like this...</para>
		<programlisting>define command{
		        command_name    no-backup-report
		        command_line    /usr/local/nagios/libexec/check_dummy 2 "CRITICAL: Results of backup job were not reported!"
		        }</programlisting>
		<para>If Nagios detects that the service results are stale, it will run the 
		<code>no-backup-report</code> command as an active service check. This causes the &plugin-dummy; 
		plugin to be executed, which returns a critical state to Nagios. The service will then go into to
		a critical state (if it isn't already there) and someone will probably get notified of the problem.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

