<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="advancedtopics-objecttricks" xreflabel="Time-Saving Tricks For Object Definitions">
	<title>Time-Saving Tricks For Object Definitions</title>
	<abstract>
		<para>
		or..."How To Preserve Your Sanity"</para>
	</abstract>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>This documentation attempts to explain how you can exploit the (somewhat) hidden 
		features of <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions">template-based object definitions</link>
		to save your sanity. How so, you ask? Several types of objects allow you to specify multiple 
		host names and/or hostgroup names in definitions, allowing you to "copy" the object defintion
		to multiple hosts or services. I'll cover each type of object that supports these features
		seperately. For starters, the object types which support this time-saving feature are as follows:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="advancedtopics-objecttricks-service">Services</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="advancedtopics-objecttricks-serviceescalation">Service escalations</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="advancedtopics-objecttricks-servicedependency">Service dependencies</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="advancedtopics-objecttricks-hostescalation">Host escalations</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="advancedtopics-objecttricks-hostdependency">Host dependencies</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="advancedtopics-objecttricks-hostgroup">Hostgroups</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Object types that are not listed above (i.e. timeperiods, commands, etc.) do not support the 
		features I'm about to describe.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Regular Expression Matching</title>
		<para>The examples I give below use <quote>standard</quote> matching of object names. If you wish, you can 
		enable regular expression matching for object names by using the 
		<link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-use_regexp_matching">use_regexp_matching</link> 
		config option. By default, regular expression matching will only be used in object names
		that contain *, ?, +, or \.. If you want regular expression matching to be used on all
		object names, enable the 
		<link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-use_true_regexp_matching">use_true_regexp_matching</link> 
		config option.
		Regular expressions can be used in any of the fields used in the examples below 
		(host names, hostgroup names, service names, and servicegroup names).</para>
		<note>
			<para>Be careful when enabling regular expression matching - you may have to
		change your config file, since some directives that you might not want to be interpreted 
		as a regular expression just might be ! Any problems should become evident once you verify 
		your configuration. 
		</para>
		</note>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>
			<anchor id="advancedtopics-objecttricks-service"/>Service Definitions</title>
		<section>
			<title>Multiple Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create identical 
			<link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-service">services</link> that
			are assigned to multiple hosts, you can specify multiple hosts in the <varname>host_name</varname> directive.
			The definition below would create a service called SOMESERVICE on hosts HOST1 through HOSTN.
			All the instances of the SOMESERVICE service would be identical (i.e. have the same
			check command, max check attempts, notification period, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define service{
    host_name                HOST1,HOST2,HOST3,...,HOSTN
    service_description      SOMESERVICE
    other service directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Hosts In Multiple Hostgroups:</title>
			<para>If you want to create identical services that are assigned to all hosts in one or
			more hostgroups, you can do so by creating a single service definition. How ? The 
			<varname>hostgroup_name</varname> directive allows you to specify the name of one or more
			hostgroups that the service should be created for. The definition below would create a 
			service called SOMESERVICE on all hosts that are members of hostgroups HOSTGROUP1 
			through HOSTGROUPN. All the instances of the SOMESERVICE service would be identical 
			(i.e. have the same check command, max check attempts, notification period, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define service{
    hostgroup_name          HOSTGROUP1,HOSTGROUP2,...,HOSTGROUPN
    service_description     SOMESERVICE
    other service directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create identical services that are assigned to all hosts 
			that are defined in your configuration files, you can use a wildcard in the <varname>host_name</varname>
			directive. The definition below would create a service called SOMESERVICE on all hosts 
			that are defined in your configuration files. All the instances of the SOMESERVICE service
			would be identical (i.e. have the same check command, max check attempts, notification
			period, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define service{
    host_name               *
    service_description     SOMESERVICE
    other service directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Excluding Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create identical services on numerous hosts or hostgroups, but 
			would like to exclude some hosts from the definition, this can be accomplished by
			preceding the host or hostgroup with a ! symbol.</para>
			<programlisting>
define service{
    host_name             HOST1,HOST2,!HOST3,!HOST4,...,HOSTN
    hostgroup_name        HOSTGROUP1,HOSTGROUP2,!HOSTGROUP3,!HOSTGROUP4,...,HOSTGROUPN
    service_description   SOMESERVICE
    other service directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>
			<anchor id="advancedtopics-objecttricks-serviceescalation"/>Service Escalation Definitions</title>
		<section>
			<title>Multiple Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create 
			<link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-serviceescalation">service escalations</link>
			for services of the same name/description that are assigned to multiple hosts, you can
			specify multiple hosts in the <varname>host_name</varname> directive. The definition below 
			would create a service escalation for services called SOMESERVICE on hosts HOST1 through
			HOSTN. All the instances of the service escalation would be identical (i.e. have 
			the same contact groups, notification interval, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define serviceescalation{
    host_name               HOST1,HOST2,HOST3,...,HOSTN
    service_description     SOMESERVICE
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Hosts In Multiple Hostgroups:</title>
			<para>If you want to create service escalations for services of the same name/description
			that are assigned to all hosts in in one or more hostgroups, you can do use the 
			<varname>hostgroup_name</varname> directive. The definition below would create a service 
			escalation for services called SOMESERVICE on all hosts that are members of hostgroups
			HOSTGROUP1 through HOSTGROUPN. All the instances of the service escalation would 
			be identical (i.e. have the same contact groups, notification interval, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define serviceescalation{
    hostgroup_name          HOSTGROUP1,HOSTGROUP2,...,HOSTGROUPN
    service_description     SOMESERVICE
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create identical service escalations for services of the same
			name/description that are assigned to all hosts that are defined in your configuration
			files, you can use a wildcard in the <varname>host_name</varname> directive. 
			The definition below would create a service escalation for all services called 
			SOMESERVICE on all hosts that are defined in your configuration files. All the 
			instances of the service escalation would be identical (i.e. have the same 
			contact groups, notification interval, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define serviceescalation{
    host_name               *
    service_description     SOMESERVICE
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Excluding Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create identical services escalations for services on numerous 
			hosts or hostgroups, but would like to exclude some hosts from the definition, this
			can be accomplished by preceding the host or hostgroup with a ! symbol.</para>
			<programlisting>
define serviceescalation{
    host_name             HOST1,HOST2,!HOST3,!HOST4,...,HOSTN
    hostgroup_name        HOSTGROUP1,HOSTGROUP2,!HOSTGROUP3,!HOSTGROUP4,...,HOSTGROUPN
    service_description   SOMESERVICE
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Services On Same Host:</title>
			<para>If you want to create 
			<link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-serviceescalation">service escalations</link> 
			for all services assigned to a particular host, you can use a wildcard in the
			<varname>service_description</varname> directive. The definition below would create a 
			service escalation for all services on host HOST1. All the instances of the service
			escalation would be identical (i.e. have the same contact groups, notification 
			interval, etc.).</para>
			<para>If you feel like being particularly adventurous, you can specify a wildcard 
			in both the <varname>host_name</varname> and <varname>service_description</varname> directives. 
			Doing so would create a service escalation for all services that you've defined in
			your configuration files.</para>
			<programlisting>
define serviceescalation{
    host_name               HOST1
    service_description     *
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Multiple Services On Same Host:</title>
			<para>If you want to create 
			<link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-serviceescalation">service escalations</link>
			for all multiple services assigned to a particular host, you can use a specify more than
			one service description in the <varname>service_description</varname> directive.
			The definition below would create a service escalation for services SERVICE1 through 
			SERVICEN on host HOST1. All the instances of the service escalation would be 
			identical (i.e. have the same contact groups, notification interval, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define serviceescalation{
    host_name               HOST1
    service_description     SERVICE1,SERVICE2,...,SERVICEN
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Services In Multiple Servicegroups:</title>
			<para>If you want to create service escalations for all services that belong in 
			one or more servicegroups, you can do use the <varname>servicegroup_name</varname> directive.
			The definition below would create service escalations for all services that are 
			members of servicegroups SERVICEGROUP1 through SERVICEGROUPN. 
			All the instances of the service escalation would be identical (i.e. have the
			same contact groups, notification interval, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define serviceescalation{
    servicegroup_name          SERVICEGROUP1,SERVICEGROUP2,...,SERVICEGROUPN
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>
			<anchor id="advancedtopics-objecttricks-servicedependency"/>Service Dependency Definitions</title>
		<section>
			<title>Multiple Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create 
			<link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-servicedependency">service dependencies</link> 
			for services of the same name/description that are assigned to multiple hosts, you can
			specify multiple hosts in the <varname>host_name</varname> and or <varname>dependent_host_name</varname> 
			directives. In the example below, service SERVICE2 on hosts HOST3 and HOST4 would be 
			dependent on service SERVICE1 on hosts HOST1 and HOST2. All the instances of the service
			dependencies would be identical except for the host names (i.e. have the same 
			notification failure criteria, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define servicedependency{
    host_name                       HOST1,HOST2
    service_description             SERVICE1
    dependent_host_name             HOST3,HOST4
    dependent_service_description   SERVICE2
    other dependency directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Hosts In Multiple Hostgroups:</title>
			<para>If you want to create service dependencies for services of the same 
			name/description that are assigned to all hosts in in one or more hostgroups, you can 
			do use the <varname>hostgroup_name</varname> and/or <varname>dependent_hostgroup_name</varname> 
			directives. In the example below, service SERVICE2 on all hosts in hostgroups HOSTGROUP3 
			and HOSTGROUP4 would be dependent on service SERVICE1 on all hosts in hostgroups HOSTGROUP1
			and HOSTGROUP2. Assuming there were five hosts in each of the hostgroups, this
			definition would be equivalent to creating 100 single service dependency definitions !
			All the instances of the service dependency would be identical except for the 
			host names (i.e. have the same notification failure criteria, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define servicedependency{
    hostgroup_name                  HOSTGROUP1,HOSTGROUP2
    service_description             SERVICE1
    dependent_hostgroup_name        HOSTGROUP3,HOSTGROUP4
    dependent_service_description   SERVICE2
    other dependency directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Services On A Host:</title>
			<para>If you want to create service dependencies for all services assigned to a 
			particular host, you can use a wildcard in the <varname>service_description</varname> and/or 
			<varname>dependent_service_description</varname> directives. In the example below, all
			services on host HOST2 would be dependent on all services on host HOST1. All 
			the instances of the service dependencies would be identical (i.e. have the
			same notification failure criteria, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define servicedependency{
    host_name                       HOST1
    service_description             *
    dependent_host_name             HOST2
    dependent_service_description   *
    other dependency directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Multiple Services On A Host:</title>
			<para>If you want to create service dependencies for multiple services assigned to 
			a particular host, you can specify more than one service description in the 
			<varname>service_description</varname> and/or <varname>dependent_service_description</varname> 
			directives as follows:</para>
			<programlisting>
define servicedependency{
    host_name                       HOST1
    service_description             SERVICE1,SERVICE2,...,SERVICEN
    dependent_host_name             HOST2
    dependent_service_description   SERVICE1,SERVICE2,...,SERVICEN
    other dependency directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Services In Multiple Servicegroups:</title>
			<para>If you want to create service dependencies for all services that belong in 
			one or more servicegroups, you can do use the <varname>servicegroup_name</varname> and/or 
			<varname>dependent_servicegroup_name</varname> directive as follows:</para>
			<programlisting>
define servicedependency{
    servicegroup_name               SERVICEGROUP1,SERVICEGROUP2,...,SERVICEGROUPN
    dependent_servicegroup_name     SERVICEGROUP3,SERVICEGROUP4,...SERVICEGROUPN
    other dependency directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<anchor id="advancedtopics-objecttricks-same_host_dependency"/>Same Host Dependencies:</title>
			<para>If you want to create service dependencies for multiple services that are 
			dependent on services on the same host, leave the <varname>dependent_host_name</varname> and 
			<varname>dependent_hostgroup_name</varname> directives empty. 
			The example below assumes that hosts HOST1 and HOST2 have at least the following 
			four services associated with them: SERVICE1, SERVICE2, SERVICE3, and SERVICE4. 
			In this example, SERVICE3 and SERVICE4 on HOST1 will be dependent on both SERVICE1 and 
			SERVICE2 on HOST1. Similiarly, SERVICE3 and SERVICE4 on HOST2 will be dependent on
			both SERVICE1 and SERVICE2 on HOST2.</para>
			<programlisting>
define servicedependency{
    host_name                       HOST1,HOST2
    service_description             SERVICE1,SERVICE2
    dependent_service_description   SERVICE3,SERVICE4
    other dependency directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>
			<anchor id="advancedtopics-objecttricks-hostescalation"/>Host Escalation Definitions</title>
		<section>
			<title>Multiple Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create 
			<link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-hostescalation">host escalations</link> 
			for multiple hosts, you can specify multiple hosts in the <varname>host_name</varname> directive.
			The definition below would create a host escalation for hosts HOST1 through HOSTN. All
			the instances of the host escalation would be identical (i.e. have the same contact 
			groups, notification interval, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define hostescalation{
    host_name              HOST1,HOST2,HOST3,...,HOSTN
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Hosts In Multiple Hostgroups:</title>
			<para>If you want to create host escalations for all hosts in in one or more
			hostgroups, you can do use the <varname>hostgroup_name</varname> directive. 
			The definition below would create a host escalation on all hosts that are
			members of hostgroups HOSTGROUP1 through HOSTGROUPN. All the instances of the
			host escalation would be identical (i.e. have the same contact groups, notification 
			interval, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define hostescalation{
    hostgroup_name            HOSTGROUP1,HOSTGROUP2,...,HOSTGROUPN
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create identical host escalations for all hosts that are defined
			in your configuration files, you can use a wildcard in the <varname>host_name</varname> directive.
			The definition below would create a hosts escalation for all hosts that are defined in 
			your configuration files. All the instances of the host escalation would be 
			identical (i.e. have the same contact groups, notification interval, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define hostescalation{
    host_name               *
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Excluding Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create identical host escalations on numerous hosts or hostgroups, but 
			would like to exclude some hosts from the definition, this can be accomplished by
			preceding the host or hostgroup with a ! symbol.</para>
			<programlisting>
define hostescalation{
    host_name             HOST1,HOST2,!HOST3,!HOST4,...,HOSTN
    hostgroup_name        HOSTGROUP1,HOSTGROUP2,!HOSTGROUP3,!HOSTGROUP4,...,HOSTGROUPN
    other escalation directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>
			<anchor id="advancedtopics-objecttricks-hostdependency"/>Host Dependency Definitions</title>
		<section>
			<title>Multiple Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create 
			<link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-hostdependency">host dependencies</link> 
			for multiple hosts, you can specify multiple hosts in the <varname>host_name</varname> 
			and/or <varname>dependent_host_name</varname> directives. The definition below would be equivalent 
			to creating six seperate host dependencies. In the example above, hosts HOST3, HOST4 
			and HOST5 would be dependent upon both HOST1 and HOST2. All the instances 
			of the host dependencies would be identical except for the host names (i.e. have 
			the same notification failure criteria, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define hostdependency{
    host_name               HOST1,HOST2
    dependent_host_name     HOST3,HOST4,HOST5
    other dependency directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>All Hosts In Multiple Hostgroups:</title>
			<para>If you want to create host escalations for all hosts in in one or more 
			hostgroups, you can do use the <varname>hostgroup_name</varname> and /or 
			<varname>dependent_hostgroup_name</varname> directives. In the example below, all hosts in
			hostgroups HOSTGROUP3 and HOSTGROUP4 would be dependent on all hosts in hostgroups
			HOSTGROUP1 and HOSTGROUP2. All the instances of the host dependencies would be
			identical except for host names (i.e. have the same notification failure criteria, etc.).</para>
			<programlisting>
define hostdependency{
    hostgroup_name                  HOSTGROUP1,HOSTGROUP2
    dependent_hostgroup_name        HOSTGROUP3,HOSTGROUP4
    other dependency directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>
			<anchor id="advancedtopics-objecttricks-hostgroup"/>Hostgroups</title>
		<section>
			<title>All Hosts:</title>
			<para>If you want to create a hostgroup that has all hosts that are defined in your 
			configuration files as members, you can use a wildcard in the <varname>members</varname>
			directive. The definition below would create a hostgroup called HOSTGROUP1 that has 
			all all hosts that are defined in your configuration files as members.</para>
			<programlisting>
define hostgroup{
    hostgroup_name          HOSTGROUP1
    members                 *
    other hostgroup directives ...
}
			</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>