<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="advancedtopics-stalking" xreflabel="State Stalking">
  <title>State Stalking</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>State "stalking" is a feature which is probably not going to used by
    most users. When enabled, it allows you to log changes in the output
    service and host checks even if the state of the host or service does not
    change. When stalking is enabled for a particular host or service, Nagios
    will watch that host or service very carefully and log any changes it sees
    in the output of check results. As you'll see, it can be very helpful to
    you in later analysis of the log files.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How Does It Work?</title>

    <para>Under normal circumstances, the result of a host or service check is
    only logged if the host or service has changed state since it was last
    checked. There are a few exceptions to this, but for the most part, that's
    the rule.</para>

    <para>If you enable stalking for one or more states of a particular host
    or service, Nagios will log the results of the host or service check if
    the output from the check differs from the output from the previous check.
    Take the following example of eight consecutive checks of a
    service:</para>

    <informaltable frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Service Check #:</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Service State:</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Service Check Output:</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Logged Normally</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Logged With Stalking</para></entry>
          </row>
		</thead>
		<tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>x</para></entry>

            <entry><para>OK</para></entry>

            <entry><para>RAID array optimal</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>x+1</para></entry>

            <entry><para>OK</para></entry>

            <entry><para>RAID array optimal</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>x+2</para></entry>

            <entry><para>WARNING</para></entry>

            <entry><para>RAID array degraded (1 drive bad, 1 hot spare
            rebuilding)</para></entry>

            <entry><para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject></para></entry>

            <entry><para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject></para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>x+3</para></entry>

            <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

            <entry><para>RAID array degraded (2 drives bad, 1 host spare
            online, 1 hot spare rebuilding)</para></entry>

            <entry><para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject></para></entry>

            <entry><para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject></para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>x+4</para></entry>

            <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

            <entry><para>RAID array degraded (3 drives bad, 2 hot spares
            online)</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>

            <entry><para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject></para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>x+5</para></entry>

            <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

            <entry><para>RAID array failed</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>

            <entry><para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject></para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>x+6</para></entry>

            <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

            <entry><para>RAID array failed</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>x+7</para></entry>

            <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

            <entry><para>RAID array failed</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>

            <entry><para>-</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>Given this sequence of checks, you would normally only see two log
    entries for this catastrophe. The first one would occur at service check
    x+2 when the service changed from an OK state to a WARNING state. The
    second log entry would occur at service check x+3 when the service changed
    from a WARNING state to a CRITICAL state.</para>

    <para>For whatever reason, you may like to have the complete history of
    this catastrophe in your log files. Perhaps to help explain to your
    manager how quickly the situation got out of control, perhaps just to
    laugh at it over a couple of drinks at the local pub...</para>

    <para>Well, if you had enabled stalking of this service for CRITICAL
    states, you would have events at x+4 and x+5 logged in addition to the
    events at x+2 and x+3. Why is this? With state stalking enabled, Nagios
    would have examined the output from each service check to see if it
    differed from the output of the previous check. If the output differed and
    the state of the service didn't change between the two checks, the result
    of the newer service check would get logged.</para>

    <para>A similiar example of stalking might be on a service that checks
    your web server. If the &plugin-http; plugin first returns a WARNING state
    because of a 404 error and on subsequent checks returns a WARNING state
    because of a particular pattern not being found, you might want to know
    that. If you didn't enable state stalking for WARNING states of the
    service, only the first WARNING state event (the 404 error) would be
    logged and you wouldn't have any idea (looking back in the archived logs)
    that future WARNING states were not due to a 404, but rather some text
    pattern that could not be found in the returned web page.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Should I Enable Stalking?</title>

    <para>First, you must decide if you have a real need to analyze archived
    log data to find the exact cause of a problem. You may decide you need
    this feature for some hosts or services, but not for all. You may also
    find that you only have a need to enable stalking for some host or service
    states, rather than all of them. For example, you may decide to enable
    stalking for WARNING and CRITICAL states of a service, but not for OK and
    UNKNOWN states.</para>

    <para>The decision to to enable state stalking for a particular host or
    service will also depend on the plugin that you use to check that host or
    service. If the plugin always returns the same text output for a
    particular state, there is no reason to enable stalking for that
    state.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How Do I Enable Stalking?</title>

    <para>You can enable state stalking for hosts and services by using the
    stalking_options directive in <link
    linkend="configuringnagios-configobject">host and service
    definitions</link>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How Does Stalking Differ From Volatile Services?</title>

    <para><link linkend="advancedtopics-volatileservices">Volatile
    services</link> are similar, but will cause notifications and event
    handlers to run. Stalking is purely for logging purposes.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Caveats</title>

    <para>You should be aware that there are some potential pitfalls with
    enabling stalking. These all relate to the reporting functions found in
    various <link linkend="thebasics-cgis">CGIs</link> (histogram, alert
    summary, etc.). Because state stalking will cause additional alert entries
    to be logged, the data produced by the reports will show evidence of
    inflated numbers of alerts.</para>

    <para>As a general rule, I would suggest that you <emphasis>not</emphasis> enable stalking for
    hosts and services without thinking things through. Still, it's there if
    you need and want it.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
