<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="thebasics-macros" xreflabel="Understanding Macros and How They Work">
	<title>Understanding Macros and How They Work</title>
	<section>
		<title>Macros</title>
		<para>One of the main features that make Nagios so flexible is the ability to use macros
		in command defintions. Macros allow you to reference information from hosts, services, and
		other sources in your commands.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Macro Substitution - How Macros Work</title>
		<para>Before Nagios executes a command, it will replace any macros it finds in the 
		command definition with their corresponding values. This macro substitution occurs for 
		all types of commands that Nagios executes - host and service checks, notifications, event
		handlers, etc.</para>
		<para>Certain macros may themselves contain other macros. These include the <code>$HOSTNOTES$</code>,
		<code>$HOSTNOTESURL$</code>, <code>$HOSTACTIONURL$</code>, <code>$SERVICENOTES$</code>, 
		<code>$SERVICENOTESURL$</code>, and <code>$SERVICEACTIONURL$</code> macros.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Example 1: Host Address Macro</title>
		<para>
		When you use host and service macros in command definitions, they refer to values for the host or
		service for which the command is being run. Let's try an example. Assuming we are using a host
		definition and a check_ping command defined like this:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
		define host{
		        host_name               linuxbox
		        address         192.168.1.2
		        check_command   check_ping
		        ...
		        }
		       
		define command{
		        command_name    check_ping
		        command_line    /usr/local/nagios/libexec/check_ping -H $HOSTADDRESS$ -w 100.0,90% -c 200.0,60%
		        }
		</programlisting>
		<para>the expanded/final command line to be executed for the host's check command would look like this:</para>
		<para><code>/usr/local/nagios/libexec/check_ping -H 192.168.1.2 -w 100.0,90% -c 200.0,60%</code></para>
		<para>Pretty simple, right? The beauty in this is that you can use a single command definition to check 
		an unlimited number of hosts. Each host can be checked with the same command definition because each host's 
		address is automatically substituted in the command line before execution.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Example 2: Command Argument Macros</title>
		<para>You can pass arguments to commands as well, which is quite handy if you'd like to keep your
		command definitions rather generic. Arguments are specified in the object (i.e. host or service)
		definition, by separating them from the command name with exclamation points (!) like so:</para>
		<programlisting>
		define service{
		        host_name               linuxbox
		        service_description     PING
		        check_command   check_ping!200.0,80%!400.0,40%
		        ...
		        }
		</programlisting>
		<para>In the example above, the service check command has two arguments (which can be 
		referenced with <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-arg">$ARGn$</link> macros). The $ARG1$ macro will 
		be "200.0,80%" and <code>$ARG2$</code> will be "400.0,40%" (both without quotes). 
		Assuming we are using the host definition given earlier and a &plugin-ping; 
		command defined like this:</para>
		<programlisting>
		define command{
		        command_name    check_ping
		        command_line    /usr/local/nagios/libexec/check_ping -H $HOSTADDRESS$ -w $ARG1$ -c $ARG2$
		        
		</programlisting>
		<para>the expanded/final command line to be executed for the service's check command would look like this:</para>
		<para><code>/usr/local/nagios/libexec/check_ping -H 192.168.1.2 -w 200.0,80% -c 400.0,40%</code></para>
		<para><tip><para>If you need to pass bang (!) characters in your command arguments, you can do so by escaping 
		them with a backslash (\). If you need to include backslashes in your command arguments, they should
		also be escaped with a backslash.</para></tip></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>On-Demand Macros</title>
		<para>Normally when you use host and service macros in command definitions, they refer to values
		for the host or service for which the command is being run. For instance, if a host check
		command is being executed for a host named "linuxbox", all the 
		<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist">standard host macros</link> will refer to values for
		that host ("linuxbox").</para>
		<para>If you would like to reference values for another host or service in a command 
		(for which the command is not being run), you can use what are called "on-demand" macros. 
		On-demand macros look like normal macros, except for the fact that they contain an identifier 
		for the host or service from which they should get their value. Here's the basic format 
		for on-demand macros:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><code>$HOSTMACRONAME:host_name$</code></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><code>$SERVICEMACRONAME:host_name:service_description$</code></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Replace <code>HOSTMACRONAME</code> and <code>SERVICEMACRONAME</code> with the name of one of the 
		standard host of service macros found <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist">here</link>.</para>
		<para>Note that the macro name is separated from the host or service identifier by a colon (:). 
		For on-demand service macros, the service identifier consists of both a host name and a service
		description - these are separated by a colon (:) as well.</para>
		<para><tip><para>On-demand service macros can contain an empty host name field. In this case 
		the name of the host associated with the service will automatically be used.</para></tip></para>
		<para>Examples of on-demand host and service macros follow:</para>
		<para><code>$HOSTDOWNTIME:myhost$                        &lt;--- On-demand host macro</code></para>
		<para><code>$SERVICESTATEID:novellserver:DS Database$    &lt;--- On-demand service macro</code></para>
		<para><code>$SERVICESTATEID::CPU Load$                   &lt;--- On-demand service macro with blank host name field</code></para>
		<para>On-demand macros are also available for hostgroup, servicegroup, contact, and contactgroup macros. For example:</para>
		<para><code>$CONTACTEMAIL:john$                          &lt;--- On-demand contact macro</code></para>
		<para><code>$CONTACTGROUPMEMBERS:linux-admins$           &lt;--- On-demand contactgroup macro</code></para>
		<para><code>$HOSTGROUPALIAS:linux-servers$               &lt;--- On-demand hostgroup macro</code></para>
		<para><code>$SERVICEGROUPALIAS:DNS-Cluster$              &lt;--- On-demand servicegroup macro</code></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>On-Demand Group Macros</title>
		<para>You can obtain the values of a macro across all contacts, hosts, or services in a specific group 
		by using a special format for your on-demand macro declaration. You do this by referencing a specific 
		host group, service group, or contact group name in an on-demand macro, like so:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><code>$HOSTMACRONAME:hostgroup_name:delimiter$</code></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><code>$SERVICEMACRONAME:servicegroup_name:delimiter$</code></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><code>$CONTACTMACRONAME:contactgroup_name:delimiter$</code></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Replace <code>HOSTMACRONAME</code>, <code>SERVICEMACRONAME</code>, and <code>CONTACTMACRONAME</code> with 
		the name of one of the standard host, service, or contact macros found 
		<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist">here</link>. The delimiter you specify is 
		used to separate macro values for each group member.</para>
		<para>For example, the following macro will return a comma-separated list of host 
		state ids for hosts that are members of the hg1 hostgroup:</para>
		<para><code>$HOSTSTATEID:hg1:,$</code></para>
		<para>This macro definition will return something that looks like this:</para>
		<para><code>0,2,1,1,0,0,2</code></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Custom Variable Macros</title>
		<para>Any <link linkend="configuringnagios-customobjectvars">custom object variables</link>
		that you define in host, service, or contact definitions are also available as macros.
		Custom variable macros are named as follows:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><code>$_HOSTvarname$</code></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><code>$_SERVICEvarname$</code></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><code>$_CONTACTvarname$</code></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Take the following host definition with a custom variable called "<code>_MACADDRESS</code>"...</para>
		<programlisting>
		define host{
		        host_name               linuxbox
		        address         192.168.1.1
		        _MACADDRESS     00:01:02:03:04:05
		        ...
		        }
		</programlisting>
		<para>The <code>_MACADDRESS</code> custom variable would be available in a macro 
		called <code>$_HOSTMACADDRESS$</code>. More information on custom object variables and how they 
		can be used in macros can be found <link linkend="configuringnagios-customobjectvars">here</link>.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Macro Cleansing</title>
		<para>Some macros are stripped of potentially dangerous shell metacharacters before being
		substituted into commands to be executed. Which characters are stripped from the macros
		depends on the setting of the <link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-illegal_macro_output_chars">illegal_macro_output_chars</link> directive. 
		The following macros are stripped of potentially dangerous characters:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-hostoutput">$HOSTOUTPUT$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-longhostoutput">$LONGHOSTOUTPUT$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-hostperfdata">$HOSTPERFDATA$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-hostackauthor">$HOSTACKAUTHOR$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-hostackcomment">$HOSTACKCOMMENT$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-serviceoutput">$SERVICEOUTPUT$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-longserviceoutput">$LONGSERVICEOUTPUT$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-serviceperfdata">$SERVICEPERFDATA$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-serviceackauthor">$SERVICEACKAUTHOR$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-serviceackcomment">$SERVICEACKCOMMENT$</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Macros as Environment Variables</title>
		<para>Most macros are made available as environment variables for easy reference by scripts or
		commands that are executed by Nagios. For purposes of security and sanity, <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-user">$USERn$</link>
		and "on-demand" host and service macros are not made available as environment variables.</para>
		<para>Environment variables that contain standard macros are named the same as their corresponding 
		macro names (listed <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist">here</link>), with "NAGIOS_" prepended to 
		their names. For example, the <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-hostname">$HOSTNAME$</link> macro would 
		be available as an environment variable named "NAGIOS_HOSTNAME".</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Available Macros</title>
		<para>A list of all the macros that are available in Nagios, as well as a chart of when they can be
		used, can be found <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist">here</link>.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

