<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="thebasics-passivechecks" xreflabel="Passive Checks">

  <title>Passive Checks</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>In most cases you'll use Nagios to monitor your hosts and services
    using regularly scheduled <link linkend="thebasics-activechecks">active
    checks</link>. Active checks can be used to "poll" a device or service for
    status information every so often. Nagios also supports a way to monitor
    hosts and services passively instead of actively. They key features of
    passive checks are as follows:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Passive checks are initiated and performed external
        applications/processes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Passive check results are submitted to Nagios for
        processing</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The major difference between active and passive checks is that
    active checks are initiated and performed by Nagios, while passive checks
    are performed by external applications.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Uses For Passive Checks</title>

    <para>Passive checks are useful for monitoring services that are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Asynchronous in nature and cannot be monitored effectively by
        polling their status on a regularly scheduled basis</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Located behind a firewall and cannot be checked actively from
        the monitoring host</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Examples of asynchronous services that lend themselves to being
    monitored passively include &protocol-snmp; traps and security
    alerts. You never know how many (if any) traps or alerts you'll receive in
    a given time frame, so it's not feasible to just monitor their status
    every few minutes.</para>

    <para>Passive checks are also used when configuring <link
    linkend="advancedtopics-distributed">distributed</link> or <link
    linkend="advancedtopics-redundancy">redundant</link> monitoring
    installations.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How Passive Checks Work</title>

    <para><informalfigure>
	<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/passivechecks.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>Here's how passive checks work in more
    detail...</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An external application checks the status of a host or
        service.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The external application writes the results of the check to the
        <link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-command_file">external command file</link>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The next time Nagios reads the external command file it will
        place the results of all passive checks into a queue for later
        processing. The same queue that is used for storing results from
        active checks is also used to store the results from passive
        checks.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Nagios will periodically execute a <link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-check_result_reaper_frequency">check result
        reaper event</link> and scan the check result queue. Each service
        check result that is found in the queue is processed in the same
        manner - regardless of whether the check was active or passive. Nagios
        may send out notifications, log alerts, etc. depending on the check
        result information.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The processing of active and passive check results is essentially
    identical. This allows for seamless integration of status information from
    external applications with Nagios.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Enabling Passive Checks</title>

    <para>In order to enable passive checks in Nagios, you'll need to do the
    following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Set <link
        linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-accept_passive_service_checks"><code>accept_passive_service_checks</code></link> directive
        is set to 1.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Set the <code>passive_checks_enabled</code> directive in your
        host and service definitions is set to 1.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If you want to disable processing of passive checks on a global
    basis, set the <link
    linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-accept_passive_service_checks"><code>accept_passive_service_checks</code></link> directive to
    0.</para>

    <para>If you would like to disable passive checks for just a few hosts or
    services, use the <code>passive_checks_enabled</code> directive in the
    host and/or service definitions to do so.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Submitting Passive Service Check Results</title>

    <para>External applications can submit passive service check results to
    Nagios by writing a PROCESS_SERVICE_CHECK_RESULT <link
    linkend="advancedtopics-extcommands">external command</link> to the
    external command file.</para>

    <para>The format of the command is as follows: <code>[&lt;timestamp&gt;]
    PROCESS_SERVICE_CHECK_RESULT;&lt;host_name&gt;;&lt;svc_description&gt;;&lt;return_code&gt;;&lt;plugin_output&gt;</code>
    where...</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>timestamp is the time in time_t format (seconds since the UNIX
        epoch) that the service check was perfomed (or submitted). Please note
        the single space after the right bracket.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>host_name is the short name of the host associated with the
        service in the service definition</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>svc_description is the description of the service as specified
        in the service definition</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>return_code is the return code of the check (0=OK, 1=WARNING,
        2=CRITICAL, 3=UNKNOWN)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>plugin_output is the text output of the service check (i.e. the
        plugin output)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note><para>A service must be defined in Nagios before you can submit
    passive check results for it! Nagios will ignore all check results for
    services that had not been configured before it was last
    (re)started.</para></note>

    <tip><para>An example shell script of how to submit passive service check
    results to Nagios can be found in the documentation on <link
    linkend="advancedtopics-volatileservices">volatile services</link>.</para></tip>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Submitting Passive Host Check Results</title>

    <para>External applications can submit passive host check results to
    Nagios by writing a PROCESS_HOST_CHECK_RESULT external command to the
    external command file.</para>

    <para>The format of the command is as follows:
    <code>[&lt;timestamp&gt;]PROCESS_HOST_CHECK_RESULT;&lt;host_name&gt;;&lt;host_status&gt;;&lt;plugin_output&gt;</code>
    where...</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>timestamp is the time in time_t format (seconds since the UNIX
        epoch) that the host check was perfomed (or submitted). Please note
        the single space after the right bracket.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>host_name is the short name of the host (as defined in the host
        definition)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>host_status is the status of the host (0=UP, 1=DOWN,
        2=UNREACHABLE)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>plugin_output is the text output of the host check</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note><para>A host must be defined in Nagios before you can submit passive
    check results for it! Nagios will ignore all check results for hosts that
    had not been configured before it was last (re)started.</para></note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Passive Checks and Host States</title>

    <para>Unlike with active host checks, Nagios does not (by default) attempt
    to determine whether or host is DOWN or UNREACHABLE with passive checks.
    Rather, Nagios takes the passive check result to be the actual state the
    host is in and doesn't try to determine the host's actual state using the
    <link linkend="thebasics-networkreachability">reachability logic</link>.
    This can cause problems if you are submitting passive checks from a remote
    host or you have a <link linkend="advancedtopics-distributed">distributed
    monitoring setup</link> where the parent/child host relationships are
    different.</para>

    <para>You can tell Nagios to translate DOWN/UNREACHABLE passive check
    result states to their "proper" state by using the <link
    linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-translate_passive_host_checks"><code>translate_passive_host_checks</code></link> variable.
    More information on how this works can be found <link
    linkend="advancedtopics-passivestatetranslation">here</link>.</para>

    <note><para>Passive host checks are normally treated as <link
    linkend="thebasics-statetypes">HARD states</link>, unless the <link
    linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-passive_host_checks_are_soft"><code>passive_host_checks_are_soft</code></link> option is
    enabled.</para></note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Submitting Passive Check Results From Remote Hosts</title>

    <para><informalfigure>
	<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/nsca.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></informalfigure>If an application that resides on the same host as
    Nagios is sending passive host or service check results, it can simply
    write the results directly to the external command file as outlined above.
    However, applications on remote hosts can't do this so easily.</para>

    <para>In order to allow remote hosts to send passive check results to the
    monitoring host, I've developed the <link linkend="nagiosaddons-addons-nsca">&name-nsca;</link> addon.
    The &name-nsca; addon consists of a daemon that runs on the Nagios hosts and a
    client that is executed from remote hosts. The daemon will listen for
    connections from remote clients, perform some basic validation on the
    results being submitted, and then write the check results directly into
    the external command file (as described above). More information on the
    &name-nsca; addon can be found <link linkend="nagiosaddons-addons-nsca">here</link>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
