<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="thebasics-servicechecks" xreflabel="Service Checks">
	<title>Service Checks</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>The basic workings of service checks are described here...</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>When Are Service Checks Performed?</title>
		<para>Services are checked by the Nagios daemon:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>At regular intervals, as defined by the <code>check_interval</code>
				and <code>retry_interval</code> options in your 
				<link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-service">service definitions</link>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>On-demand as needed for 
				<link linkend="advancedtopics-dependencychecks">predictive service dependency
				checks</link>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>On-demand checks are performed as part of the 
		<link linkend="advancedtopics-dependencychecks">predictive service dependency check</link>
		logic. These checks help ensure that the dependency logic is as accurate as possible.
		If you don't make use of <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-servicedependency">service 
		dependencies</link>, Nagios won't perform any on-demand service checks.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Cached Service Checks</title>
		<para>The performance of on-demand service checks can be significantly improved by 
		implementing the use of cached checks, which allow Nagios to forgo executing a
		service check if it determines a relatively recent check result will do 
		instead. Cached checks will only provide a performance increase if you are 
		making use of <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-servicedependency">service 
		dependencies</link>. More information on cached checks can be found 
		<link linkend="advancedtopics-cachedchecks">here</link>.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Dependencies and Checks</title>
		<para>You can define <link linkend="configuringnagios-objectdefinitions-servicedependency">service 
		execution dependencies</link> that prevent Nagios from checking the status of a service
		depending on the state of one or more other services. More information on
		dependencies can be found <link linkend="advancedtopics-dependencies">here</link>.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Parallelization of Service Checks</title>
		<para>Scheduled service checks are run in parallel. When Nagios needs to run a scheduled 
		service check, it will initiate the service check and then return to doing other work
		(running host checks, etc). The service check runs in a child process that was fork()ed
		from the main Nagios daemon. When the service check has completed, the child process 
		will inform the main Nagios process (its parent) of the check results. The main Nagios
		process then handles the check results and takes appropriate action (running event 
		handlers, sending notifications, etc.).</para>
		<para>On-demand service checks are also run in parallel if needed. As mentioned 
		earlier, Nagios can forgo the actual execution of an on-demand service check if
		it can use the cached results from a relatively recent service check.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Service States</title>
		<para>Services that are checked can be in one of four different states:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>OK</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>WARNING</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>UNKNOWN</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>CRITICAL</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Service State Determination</title>
		<para>Service checks are performed by <link linkend="thebasics-plugins">plugins</link>, which
		can return a state of OK, WARNING, UNKNOWN, or CRITICAL. These plugin states directly translate 
		to service states. For example, a plugin which returns a WARNING state will cause a service 
		to have a WARNING state.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Services State Changes</title>
		<para>When Nagios checks the status of services, it will be able to detect when a service 
		changes between OK, WARNING, UNKNOWN, and CRITICAL states and take appropriate action.
		These state changes result in different <link linkend="thebasics-statetypes">state types</link>
		(HARD or SOFT), which can trigger <link linkend="advancedtopics-eventhandlers">event handlers</link> 
		to be run and <link linkend="thebasics-notifications">notifications</link> to be sent 
		out. Service state changes can also trigger on-demand 
		<link linkend="thebasics-hostchecks">host checks</link>. Detecting and dealing with 
		state changes is what Nagios is all about.</para>
		<para>When services change state too frequently they are considered to be <quote>flapping</quote>.
		Nagios can detect when services start flapping, and can suppress notifications until 
		flapping stops and the service's state stabilizes. More information on the flap detection
		logic can be found <link linkend="advancedtopics-flapping">here</link>.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

