<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="development-epnplugins"
         xreflabel="Developing Plugins For Use With Embedded Perl">
  <title>Developing Plugins For Use With Embedded Perl</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Stanley Hopcroft has worked with the embedded Perl interpreter quite
    a bit and has commented on the advantages/disadvanges of using it. He has
    also given several helpful hints on creating Perl plugins that work
    properly with the embedded interpreter. The majority of this documentation
    comes from his comments.</para>

    <para>It should be noted that <quote>ePN</quote>, as used in this documentation, refers
    to embedded Perl Nagios, or if you prefer, Nagios compiled with an
    embedded Perl interpreter.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Target Audience</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Average Perl developers; those with an appreciation of the
        languages powerful features without knowledge of internals or an in
        depth knowledge of those features.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Those with a utilitarian appreciation rather than a great depth
        of understanding.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If you are happy with Perl objects, name management, data
        structures, and the debugger, that's probably sufficient.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Things you should do when developing a Perl Plugin (ePN or
    not)</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Always always generate some output</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Use 'use utils' and import the stuff it exports ($TIMEOUT
        %ERRORS &amp;print_revision &amp;support)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Have a look at how the standard Perl plugins do their stuff
        e.g.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Always exit with $ERRORS{CRITICAL}, $ERRORS{OK}, etc.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Use getopt to read command line arguments</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Manage timeouts</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Call print_usage (supplied by you) when there are no command
            line arguments</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Use standard switch names (eg H 'host', V 'version')</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Things you must do to develop a Perl plugin for ePN</title>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code language="perl">&lt;DATA&gt;</code> can not be used; use
        here documents instead e.g.</para>

        <programlisting>
				my $data = &lt;&lt;DATA;
				portmapper 100000
				portmap 100000
				sunrpc 100000
				rpcbind 100000
				rstatd 100001
				rstat 100001
				rup 100001
				..
				DATA

				%prognum = map { my($a, $b) = split; ($a, $b) } split(/\n/, $data) ;
				</programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code language="perl">BEGIN</code> blocks will not work as you
        expect. May be best to avoid.</para>
      </listitem>

     <listitem><para>Ensure that it
	is squeaky clean at compile time i.e.
	</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>use strict
	</para></listitem><listitem><para>use perl -w (other switches [T
	notably] may not help)</para></listitem><listitem><para>use perl -c
	</para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para>Avoid
	lexical variables (my) with global scope as a means of passing <emphasis
	role='underline'>variable</emphasis> data into subroutines. In fact this
	is <emphasis role='underline'>fatal</emphasis> if the subroutine is
	called by the plugin more than once when the check is run.  Such
	subroutines act as 'closures' that lock the global lexicals first value
	into subsequent calls of the subroutine. If however, your global is
	read-only (a complicated structure for example) this is not a problem.
	What Bekman <ulink
	url='http://perl.apache.org/docs/1.0/guide/'>recommends you do
	instead</ulink>, is any of the following:
	</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>make the subroutine anonymous and
	call it via a code ref e.g.</para><programlisting><![CDATA[turn this                     into  

	my $x = 1 ;                   my $x = 1 ;
	sub a { .. Process $x ... }   $a_cr = sub { ... Process $x ... } ;
	.                             .
	.                             .
	a ;                           &$a_cr ;
	$x = 2                        $x = 2 ;
	a ;                           &$a_cr ;

	# anon closures __always__ rebind the current lexical value
	]]></programlisting></listitem><listitem><para>put the global lexical and
	the subroutine using it in their own package (as an object or a module)
	</para></listitem><listitem><para>pass info to subs as references or
	aliases (\$lex_var or $_[n])</para></listitem><listitem><para>replace
	lexicals with package globals and exclude them from 'use strict'
	objections with 'use vars qw(global1 global2 ..)'
	</para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Be aware of where you can get more information.</para>

        <para>Useful information can be had from the usual suspects (the
        O'Reilly books, plus Damien Conways <quote>Object Oriented Perl</quote>) but for
        the really useful stuff in the right context start at Stas Bekman's
        mod_perl guide at <ulink
        url="http://perl.apache.org/guide/">http://perl.apache.org/guide/</ulink>.</para>

        <para>This wonderful book sized document has nothing whatsoever about
        Nagios, but all about writing Perl programs for the embedded Perl
        interpreter in Apache (ie Doug MacEacherns mod_perl).</para>

        <para>The perlembed manpage is essential for context and
        encouragement.</para>

        <para>On the basis that Lincoln Stein and Doug MacEachern know a thing
        or two about Perl and embedding Perl, their book 'Writing Apache
        Modules with Perl and C' is almost certainly worth looking at.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Be aware that your plugin may return strange values with an ePN
        and that this is likely to be caused by the problem in item #4
        above</para>
      </listitem>

     <listitem><para>Be prepared to
	debug via:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>having a test ePN and
	</para></listitem><listitem><para>adding print statements to your plugin
	to display variable values to STDERR (can't use STDOUT)
	</para></listitem><listitem><para>adding print statements to p1.pl to
	display what ePN thinks your plugin is before it tries to run it (vi)
	</para></listitem><listitem><para>running the ePN in foreground mode
	(probably in conjunction with the former recommendations)
	</para></listitem><listitem><para>use the 'Deparse' module on your
	plugin to see how the parser has optimised it and what the interpreter
	will actually get. (see 'Constants in Perl' by Sean M. Burke, The Perl
	Journal, Fall 2001)
	</para><screen>perl -MO::Deparse &lt;your_program&gt;</screen></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Be aware of what ePN is transforming your plugin too, and if all
        else fails try and debug the transformed version.</para>

        <para>As you can see below p1.pl rewrites your plugin as a subroutine
        called 'hndlr' in the package named
        'Embed::&lt;something_related_to_your_plugin_file_name&gt;'.</para>

        <para>Your plugin may be expecting command line arguments in @ARGV so
        pl.pl also assigns @_ to @ARGV.</para>

        <para>This in turn gets 'eval' ed and if the eval raises an error (any
        parse error and run error), the plugin gets chucked out.</para>

        <para>The following output shows how a test ePN transformed the
        &plugin-rpc; plugin before attempting to execute it. Most of the code
        from the actual plugin is not shown, as we are interested in only the
        transformations that the ePN has made to the plugin). For clarity,
        transformations are shown in red:</para>

        <programlisting>
				                package main;
				                use subs 'CORE::GLOBAL::exit';
				                sub CORE::GLOBAL::exit { die "ExitTrap: $_[0] 
				(Embed::check_5frpc)"; }
				                package Embed::check_5frpc; sub hndlr { shift(@_);
				@ARGV=@_;
				#! /usr/bin/perl -w
				#
				# check_rpc plugin for Nagios
				#
				# usage:
				#    check_rpc host service
				#
				# Check if an rpc serice is registered and running
				# using rpcinfo - $proto $host $prognum 2&gt;&amp;1 |";
				#
				# Use these hosts.cfg entries as examples
				#
				# command[check_nfs]=/some/path/libexec/check_rpc $HOSTADDRESS$ nfs
				# service[check_nfs]=NFS;24x7;3;5;5;unix-admin;60;24x7;1;1;1;;check_rpc
				#
				# initial version: 3 May 2000 by Truongchinh Nguyen and Karl DeBisschop
				# current status: $Revision: 1.19 $
				#
				# Copyright Notice: GPL
				#
				... rest of plugin code goes here (it was removed for brevity) ...
				}
				</programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Don't use 'use diagnostics' in a plugin run by your production
        ePN. I think it causes__all__ the Perl plugins to return
        CRITICAL.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Consider using a mini embedded Perl C program to check your
        plugin. This is not sufficient to guarantee your plugin will perform
        Ok with an ePN but if the plugin fails this test it will certainly
        fail with your ePN. [ A sample mini ePN is included in the
        <filename class="directory">contrib/</filename> directory of the Nagios distribution for
        use in testing Perl plugins. Change to the
        <filename class="directory">contrib/</filename> directory and type <command>make
        mini_epn</command> to compile it. It must be executed from the same
        directory that the p1.pl file resides in (this file is distributed
        with Nagios). ]</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>

