<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="development-pluginapi" xreflabel="Nagios Plugin API">
	<title>Nagios Plugin API</title>
	<section>
		<title>Other Resources</title>
		<para>If you're looking at writing your own plugins for Nagios, please make sure to
		visit these other resources:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The official <ulink url="&url-sourceforge-projects;nagiosplug/">Nagios
				plugin project website</ulink>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The official <ulink url="http://nagiosplug.sourceforge.net/developer-guidelines.html">
				Nagios plugin development guidelines</ulink>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Plugin Overview</title>
		<para>Scripts and executables must do two things (at a minimum) in order to function as Nagios plugins:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Exit with one of several possible return values</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Return at least one line of text output to <varname>STDOUT</varname></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>The inner workings of your plugin are unimportant to Nagios. Your plugin could check the status 
		of a TCP port, run a database query, check disk free space, or do whatever else it needs to check
		something. The details will depend on what needs to be checked - that's up to you.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Return Code</title>
		<para>Nagios determines the status of a host or service by evaluating the return code from plugins. 
		The following tables shows a list of valid return codes, along with their corresponding service or host states.</para>
		<informaltable frame="all">
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>Plugin Return Code</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>Service State</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>Host State</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>0</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>OK</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>UP</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>1</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>WARNING</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>UP or DOWN/UNREACHABLE*</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>2</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>CRITICAL</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>DOWN/UNREACHABLE</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>3</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>UNKNOWN</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>DOWN/UNREACHABLE</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
		<note><para>If the <link linkend="configuringnagios-configmain-use_aggressive_host_checking">use_aggressive_host_checking</link> option is enabled, return codes 
		of 1 will result in a host state of DOWN or UNREACHABLE. Otherwise return codes of 1 will result in a
		host state of UP. The process by which Nagios determines whether or not a host is DOWN or UNREACHABLE 
		is discussed <link linkend="thebasics-networkreachability">here</link>.</para></note>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Plugin Output Spec</title>
		<para>At a minimum, plugins should return at least one of text output. Beginning with Nagios 3, plugins 
		can optionally return multiple lines of output. Plugins may also return optional performance data that 
		can be processed by external applications. The basic format for plugin output is shown below:</para>
		<para>TEXT OUTPUT | OPTIONAL PERFDATALONG TEXT LINE 1LONG TEXT LINE 2...LONG TEXT LINE N | PERFDATA LINE 2PERFDATA LINE 3...PERFDATA LINE N</para>
		<para>The performance data (shown in orange) is optional. If a plugin returns performance data in 
		its output, it must separate the performance data from the other text output using a pipe (|) symbol. 
		Additional lines of long text output (shown in blue) are also optional.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Plugin Output Examples</title>
		<para>Let's see some examples of possible plugin output...</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Case 1: One line of output (text only)</emphasis></para><para>Assume we have a plugin that returns one line of output 
		that looks like this:</para>
		<screen>DISK OK - free space: / 3326 MB (56%);</screen>
		<para>If this plugin was used to perform a service check, the entire line of output will be stored 
		in the <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-serviceoutput"><varname>$SERVICEOUTPUT$</varname></link> macro.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Case 2: One line of output (text and perfdata)</emphasis></para><para>A plugin can return optional performance data 
		for use by external applications. To do this, the performance data must be separated from the 
		text output with a pipe (|) symbol like such:</para>
		<screen>DISK OK - free space: / 3326 MB (56%);</screen>
		<screen> | </screen>
		<screen>/=2643MB;5948;5958;0;5968</screen>
		<para>If this plugin was used to perform a service check, the red portion of output (left of the pipe separator) will be stored in the <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-serviceoutput">$SERVICEOUTPUT$</link> macro and the orange portion of output (right of the pipe separator) will be stored in the 
		<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-serviceperfdata">$SERVICEPERFDATA$</link> macro.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Case 3: Multiple lines of output (text and perfdata)</emphasis></para><para>A plugin optionally return multiple lines
		of both text output and perfdata, like such:</para>
		<screen>DISK OK - free space: / 3326 MB (56%); | /=2643MB;5948;5958;0;5968/ 15272 MB (77%);/boot 68 MB (69%);/home 69357 MB (27%);/var/log 819 MB (84%); | /boot=68MB;88;93;0;98/home=69357MB;253404;253409;0;253414 /var/log=818MB;970;975;0;980</screen>
		<para>If this plugin was used to perform a service check, the red portion of first line of output 
		(left of the pipe separator) will be stored in the <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-serviceoutput">$SERVICEOUTPUT$</link> macro. 
		The orange portions of the first and subsequent lines are concatenated (with spaces) are stored 
		in the <link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-serviceperfdata">$SERVICEPERFDATA$</link> macro. The blue portions of the 2nd - 5th lines 
		of output will be concatenated (with escaped newlines) and stored in 
		<link linkend="thebasics-macrolist-longserviceoutput">$LONGSERVICEOUTPUT$</link> the macro.</para>
		<para>The final contents of each macro are listed below:</para>
		<informaltable frame="all">
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>Macro</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>Value</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>$SERVICEOUTPUT$</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>DISK OK - free space: / 3326 MB (56%);</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>$SERVICEPERFDATA$</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>/=2643MB;5948;5958;0;5968 /boot=68MB;88;93;0;98 /home=69357MB;253404;253409;0;253414 /var/log=818MB;970;975;0;980</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>$LONGSERVICEOUTPUT$</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>/ 15272 MB (77%);\n/boot 68 MB (69%);\n/var/log 819 MB (84%);</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
		<para>With regards to multiple lines of output, you have the following options for returning performance data:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>You can choose to return no performance data whatsoever</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>You can return performance data on the first line only</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>You can return performance data only in subsequent lines (after the first)</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>You can return performance data in both the first line and subsequent lines (as shown above)</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Plugin Output Length Restrictions</title>
		<para>Nagios will only read the first 4 KB of data that a plugin returns. This is done in order to
		prevent runaway plugins from dumping megs or gigs of data back to Nagios. This 4 KB output limit is 
		fairly easy to change if you need. Simply edit the value of the MAX_PLUGIN_OUTPUT_LENGTH definition in 
		the include/nagios.h.in file of the source code distribution and recompile Nagios. There's nothing 
		else you need to change!</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>
		<para>If you're looking for some example plugins to study, I would recommend that you download the 
		official Nagios plugins and look through the code for various C, Perl, and shell script plugins.
		Information on obtaining the official Nagios plugins can be found <link linkend="thebasics-plugins">here</link>.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Perl Plugins</title>
		<para>Nagios features an optional <link linkend="advancedtopics-embeddedperl">embedded Perl 
		interpreter</link> which can speed up the execution of Perl plugins. More information 
		on developing Perl plugins for use with the embedded Perl interpreter can be found 
		<link linkend="advancedtopics-embeddedperl">here</link>.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

