<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "../all-entities.ent">
  %all.entities;
]
>
<chapter id="gettingstarted-beginners">
  <title>Advice for Beginners</title>

<remark>Chapitre terminé</remark>
  
  <para>
  Congratulations on choosing Nagios! Nagios is quite powerful and
  flexible, but it can take a lot of work to get it configured just the way
  you'd like. Once you become familiar with how it works and what it can do
  for you, you'll never want to be without it&nbsp;:-) Here are some important
  things to keep in mind for first-time Nagios users:
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Relax - it's going to take some
      time.</emphasis> Don't expect to be able to get things working exactly
      the way you want them right off the bat. it's not that easy. Setting up
      Nagios can involve a bit of work - partly because of the options that
      Nagios offers, partly because you need to know what to monitor on your
      network (and how best to do it).
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Use the quickstart instructions.</emphasis>
      The <link linkend="gettingstarted-quickstart">Quickstart installation 
      guide</link> is designed to get most new users up and running with a 
      basic Nagios setup fairly quickly. Within 20 minutes you can have Nagios 
      installed and monitoring your local system. Once that's complete, you can 
      move on to learning how to configure Nagios to do more.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Read the documentation.</emphasis> Nagios
      can be tricky to configure when you've got a good grasp of what's going
      on, and nearly impossible if you don't. Make sure you read the
      documentation (particularly the sections on <quote>Configuring Nagios</quote> and
      <quote>The Basics</quote>). Save the advanced topics for when you've got a good
      understanding of the basics.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Seek the help of others.</emphasis> If
      you've read the documentation, reviewed the sample config files, and are
      still having problems, send an email message describing your problems to
      the <email>nagios-users</email> mailing list. Due to the amount of
      work that I have to do for this project, I am unable to answer most of
      the questions that get sent directly to me, so your best source of help
      is going to be the mailing list. If you've done some background reading
      and you provide a good problem description, odds are that someone will
      give you some pointers on getting things working properly. More
      information on subscribing to the mailing lists or searching the list archives 
      can be found at <ulink url="&url-nagios;support/">&url-nagios;support/</ulink>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</chapter>

